the pigeons said.
None of the animals ever mentioned Molly again.
In January, there came bitterly hard weather.
The earth was like iron, and nothing could be done in the fields.
Many meetings were held in the big barn, and the pigs occupied themselves with
planning out the work of the coming season.
It had come to be accepted that the pigs, who were manifestly cleverer than
the other animals, should decide all questions of farm policy, though their decisions had to be
ratified by a majority vote.
This arrangement would have worked well enough if it had not been for the
disputes between Snowball and Napoleon.
These two disagreed at every point where disagreement was possible.
If one of them suggested sowing a bigger acreage with barley, the other was
certain to demand a bigger acreage of oats. And if one of them said that such
and such a field was just right for cabbages, the other would declare that
it was useless for anything except roots.
Each had his own following, and there were some violent debates.
At the meetings, Snowball often won over the majority by his brilliant speeches,
but Napoleon was better at canvassing support for himself in between times.
He was especially successful with the sheep.
Of late, the sheep had taken to bleating "Four legs good, two legs bad."
both in and out of season, and they often interrupted the meeting with this.
It was noticed that they were especially liable to break into Four legs good, two legs bad.
at crucial moments in Snowball's speeches.
Snowball had made a close study of some back numbers of the Farmer and Stock
Breeder, which he had found in the farmhouse, and was full of plans for
innovations and improvements.
He talked learnedly about field drains, silage, and basic slag, and had worked
out a complicated scheme for all the animals to drop their dung directly in
the fields at a different spot every day to save the labor of cartage.
Napoleon produced no schemes of his own, but said quietly that Snowball's would come to nothing,
and seemed to be biding his time.
But of all their controversies, none was so bitter as the one that took place over the windmill.
In the long pasture, not far from the farm buildings, there was a small knoll,
which was the highest point on the farm.
After surveying the ground, Snowball declared that this was just the place for a windmill,
which could be made to operate a dynamo and supply the farm with electrical power.
This would light the stalls and warm them in winter, and would also run a
circular saw, a chaff cutter, a mangel slicer, and an electric milking machine.
The animals had never heard of anything of this kind before,
for the farm was an old-fashioned one and had only the most primitive machinery.
And they listened in astonishment while Snowball conjured up pictures of
fantastic machines which would do their work for them while they grazed at their
ease in the fields or improved their minds with reading and conversation.
Within a few weeks, Snowball's plans for the windmill were fully worked out.
The mechanical details came mostly from three books, which had belonged to Mr.
Jones.
1,000 useful things to do about the house, Every Man His Own Bricklayer,
and Electricity for Beginners.
Snowball used as his study a shed, which had once been used for incubators and
had a smooth wooden floor suitable for drawing on.
He was closeted there for hours at a time, with his books held open by a stone and
with a piece of chalk gripped between the knuckles of his trotter, he would
move rapidly to and fro, drawing in line after line and uttering little whimpers of excitement.
Gradually, the plans grew into a complicated mass of cranks and
cogwheels, covering more than half the floor, which the other animals found
completely unintelligible but very impressive.
All of them came to look at Snowball's drawings at least once a day.
Even the hens and ducks came and were at pains not to tread on the chalk marks.
Only Napoleon held aloof.
He had declared himself against the windmill from the start.
One day, however, he arrived unexpectedly to examine the plans.
He walked heavily round the shed, looked closely at every detail of the plans,
and snuffed at them once or twice, then stood for a little while
contemplating them out of the corner of his eye.
Then, suddenly, he lifted his leg, urinated over the plans, and walked out
without uttering a word.
The whole farm was deeply divided on the subject of the windmill.
Snowball did not deny that to build it would be a difficult business.
Stone would have to be quarried and built up into walls, then the sails
would have to be made, and after that, there would be need for dynamos and cables.
How these were to be procured, Snowball did not say.
But he maintained that it could all be done in a year.
And thereafter, he declared so much labor would be saved that the animals
would only need to work 3 days a week.
Napoleon, on the other hand, argued that the great need of the moment was to
increase food production and that if they wasted time on the windmill, they
would all starve to death.
The animals formed themselves into two factions under the slogans,
>> "Vote for Snowball and the 3-day week."
>> and >> "Vote for Napoleon and the full manger."
>> Benjamin was the only animal who did not side with either faction.
He refused to believe either that food would become more plentiful or that the
windmill would save work.
"Windmill or no windmill," he said,